Anguishes During Daily Life and 108 Bowing
I have recently started
my hundred days of prayer.
While I bow or meditate,
all kinds of distractions
from past, present and future come to me.
I don't know why this happens.
This bothers me immensely.
Also during my daily life,
I think to myself as I talk about others,
'I shouldn't talk bad about others.
I shouldn't interfere.'
And yet I find myself saying
the exact same thing once again.
Then I hate myself
for living the way I do.
While sitting still for meditation,
we expect our body and mind to
be peaceful.
And yet thoughts on friends, future plans,
imaginations flow continuously
like a river.
We call such wandering thoughts anguishes.
As anguishes continuously arise,
we fail to get rid of them no matter
how hard we try.
The same thing happens during
bowing practice.
Why does this happen and
what should we do?
In Springtime, flowers blossom
on branches.
Green leaves also come out.
Dark-colored branches produce such pretty
flowers.
Where do these flowers come from?
The leaves are so pretty.
Where do they come from?
It is such a mystery.
And yet there are causes that make
flowers bloom and leaves come out.
Though we cannot see them
from the outside,
there are conditions and causes hidden in
the branches.
Causes lead to such consequences.
There is no consequence without a cause
When seeing consequences without knowing
the cause,
we consider them mysterious.
We get flustered and surprised.
And yet once we realize the cause,
they are nothing mysterious nor
worth being flustered about.
People were once frightened over solar
eclipses
and believed a firedog had
swallowed the sun.
Hence they held certain rituals.
But now we know the real cause of them.
When the sun, moon and earth are aligned
in a line,
the moon's shadow blocks
sunlight.
The shadow covers the sun.
That's all there is to it.
As we know the cause,
there is nothing mysterious or
surprising about it.
We consider this a scientific mindset.
Buddhism also works this way.
Since people are unaware of the emotional
and mental aspects,
they get surprised, flustered and
mystified.
If we look into them carefully in an
analytical manner,
we can understand the
logic behind them.
Then there is nothing surprising nor
mysterious about them.
In order to achieve what we want,
we remove causes.
Once there is no cause, there is
no consequence.
We call this process
'meditation practice'.
When we sit and meditate,
meditation is not just about sitting
still in one place.
Every meditation has a task whatever it
may be.
In breath meditation, you acknowledge
your breath moving in and out.
If you are aware of an in-breath as an
in-breath, an out-breath as an out-breath,
a deep breath as deep and a shallow
breath as shallow,
then you are awake to your breath.
Your mind is entirely focused
and aware to it.
If your meditation task is a koan,
you concentrate on the koan.
If your meditation task is to observe
body sensations,
you concentrate on your body sensations.
We give different names to meditations
depending on the task.
But the principle applies the same. You
place your attention on one thing and focus.
Focusing on one thing means you're in an
awakened state.
There are things that obstruct your
concentration during meditation.
The first obstruction comes from external
distractions that derail your mind.
While you are focusing on your task,
you hear (inaudible)
noises of people checking their bags,
phone's ringing,
people talking to each other.
You inevitably lose your concentration. yes?
(Audience) yes
You inevitably lose your concentration
While listening to a dharma talk,
assume a person comes up here
and starts bowing.
Your mind starts to wander, does it not?
(Audience) It does
It does as you see, hear, smell, taste and
feel things. You lose your concentration.
You lose your mind to external
distractions.
Hence you need to protect
your mind from them.
Regardless of what you see, hear, smell,
taste or feel,
you should leave them as is and focus
your concentration on yourself only.
You can wish for no external distractions,
yet you don't have control over
such things.
You may think, 'I wish I couldn't hear
those cars from outside'.
The more you wish you won't hear them,
the better you hear them, no?
(Audience) yes
yes
The more you wish you won't hear them,
the louder they will seem.
And yet if you focus on your breath and
concentrate,
car sounds are still there
but they can't distract you from
concentrating.
Then you almost don't hear them anymore.
Have the sounds gone away?
No, they haven't.
The sounds remain, yet they no longer
distract your focus.
Beginners close their eyes to avoid
external distractions that disturb them.
With eyes closed, the mind doesn't wander
to visual distractions.
When in a quiet place,
the mind doesn't wander to
audial distractions.
And without foods and odors,
you're less inclined to get distracted
from external forces.
That is why we choose to meditate at a
quiet place.
Having said that, meditating at a quiet
place indicates that you are not complete.
It's for beginners. Once you have enough
practice,
you should be able to meditate anywhere
without losing focus.
The first obstructions are external
distractions.
The second ones are physical sensations.
Once you sit a while, your legs go to
sleep,
your back hurts. Your attention
moves to your legs.
Hence your concentration level falls.
You wonder whether you should
stretch or fold your legs.
Sitting still, your face starts itching.
You think bugs might be biting you.
You want to move around.
This hinders your concentration.
so no matter what sensations arise
in your body - whether your legs are numb,
whether your face itches
or your back hurts, leave them alone.
Don't let it bother you.
Focus only on your breath
and let everything else go.
The third obstruction are thoughts
that arise. You think of the past,
You think of tomorrow.
Thoughts usually don't come when they are
most needed.
And yet during meditation, all kinds of
brilliant thoughts come to you.
You even think of events that
just happened.
Your mind wanders off.
You lose yourself in your thoughts
and soon realize that you are far off
as if in a dream.
'Ah! I lost myself'
And you don't even remember
when you lost your focus on your breath
Many anguishes arise.
As we have bodies, we sense
sounds and shapes.
Our minds have a constant flow of
thought.
They don't go away even if you
want them to.
Sensations naturally arise even if you
don't want them to.
Thoughts arise even if you don't want
them to.
Sounds exist, and our body exists.
Hence our body senses them.
As we store many experiences in our
consciousness, live broadcasting stops,
recorded broadcasting starts playing
the moment we close our eyes.
All this happens for a reason.
It happens even if you don't want it do.
Therefore you shouldn't be bothered by it.
The more you wonder why they appear,
shake your head and deny them, the more
they'll appear.
It's like as if you're chasing off dust.
If you try shaking off dust, it only gets
dustier.
Leave the dust alone, it will naturally
settle down.
While you concentrate on a koan or your
breath,
don't move your body no matter what sound
or sensation you feel.
Don't follow any thoughts arising in your
head.
Just focus on the meditation task that is
given to you.
Beginners easily get distracted.
When this happens, come back to
your task again and again and again
If you do this,
random thoughts will no
longer make you lose focus.
Sounds from outside will no longer hinder
your observation of the breath.
Pains in your body will be pains as is.
You'll be able to focus on
meditation only.
Then your mind will become
calmer and clearer.
In short, it is natural to experience
anguishes arise within you.
To wonder why anguishes arise
would be to be adding more anguishes
to your existing ones.
Hence just let them flow like water and
focus on your given task.
Then they will naturally disappear
over time.
The same logic applies when you bow.
There is always a task when bowing.
The task itself is important.
Is watching your breath during
bows considered the task itself?
It is not. What you are praying for
during bows is the task.
For those who received koan, the koan is
the task.
In breathing meditation, examining the
breath is the task.
In somatic meditation, examining body
sensations is the task.
In Jungto, your prayer words are your
task while bowing.
If you received prayer words,
I will be humble, then your task is to
recite them as you bow.
Now you shouldn't be focusing on reciting
the words only.
You should be looking back at your day to
realize you haven't been humble.
You received the task to be humble,
and yet you were high on your horse again.
You had raised your voice.
You should think, 'Ah, I forgot to be
humble at that very moment.'
As you failed, you should be sorry.
I'm not saying you should be sorry
for your wrongdoing.
You should have remembered your task
yet you lost it.
Hence you should be sorry for not keeping
to your task.
It's about being mindful and acknowledging
'I've been arrogant again'.
Without a task, you won't know your
wrongdoings.
You take things for granted.
With a task, you have a task to fail on.
Hence it enables you to repent.
You realize, 'Ah, I lost it'.
Now your repentance becomes earnest.
'Ah, I let it slip away. I'm sorry.'
Bowing isn't just about reciting again
and again, 'I will be humble'.
It's about acknowledging when you've
failed to follow through,
and reflecting upon yourself saying
'Ah, I've missed it again.'
Repentance is about acknowledging your
mistake.
Saying 'I'm stupid, I can't even follow
through'
is not repentance. It is regret.
Regretting is to be in a negative
mindset.
We call this the 'wrong way'.
Regretting indicates that you think you
shouldn't have done wrong and yet you have
Hence you're unable to forgive yourself
for having done wrong.
You are ashamed of yourself for what
you've done. You hate yourself.
That is the mind of regret.
Repentance is about acknowledging
your wrongdoing.
It's about acknowledging the fact as is.
Once you acknowledge it,
what automatically comes to mind is,
'I will not miss it again'.
This we call an aspiration.
'I missed it but I won't next time'.
'I fell but I shall get back up.'
Such thoughts are all interconnected.
Hence repentance means repenting past
wrongdoings while vowing not to repeat them.
Saying 'Why blame myself only?
What about others?'
is to justify your wrongdoings.
Saying 'I'm such an idiot, why do I keep
failing?'
is to be unforgiving of
yourself.
Repentance is simply acknowledging your
mistakes as mistakes.
It's about noticing mistakes and
challenging yourself once again.
You vow to do right next time,
hence you bow.
When you've done right, do you
not raise your head high?
You straighten your shoulders and back,
you raise your chin.
But when you've done wrong,
you lower your head, shoulders and back.
You kneel and put your forehead to the ground.
You stoop down entirely.
By physically doing so you let go
of your thoughts within.
At that moment,
there are no other to be held as you are
focused on the activity itself.
But if you bow without focusing on the
task, all kinds of thoughts arise.
You'd be meaninglessly bowing thinking,
'Why the hell am I bowing?'
'Does this even help?'
(inaudible)
(Audience Laughter)
this is how people bow.
Now bowing itself is good physical
exercise for your body.
(Audience Laughter)
It releases some of your stress.
Hence bowing without a purpose still has
its benefits.
And yet your life won't change this way.
Your state of mind needs to change.
Once you acknowledge and repent
thinking to yourself,
'Ah, I made a mistake. I should try again'
'Ah, I missed again, lets try again',
when similar situations arise,
your will to fulfill the task grows
stronger even if you fail.
Saying 'I failed once again.'
'I failed once again.'
'Since I failed 10 times, I'll never make it'
this is not true repentance.
These are negative thoughts.
If you fail 100 times, you should try
the 101st time.
The more you fail, the stronger your will
will become.
Hence you will realize at a certain point.
At a moment you become arrogant,
you'll notice it.
At the very moment,
you'll become aware.
Change yourself right then and there.
If you don't, you'll feel uneasy.
Once you change yourself,
you'll immediately find comfort.
You'll experience it and think,
'Ah, so this is how the mind works.'
You'll think you've got it, but you'll
fail again.
You'll fail a hundred times only to
succeed once.
But from then onwards, you'll succeed
every 50th time.
Then you'll succeed every 10th time,
then every 5th time.
Wouldn't that mean you are changing or
not? It means you're getting better.
Next time you'll succeed once every 2
trials,
then 4 times out of 5, 9 times out of 10.
There will be times you fail.
At first you'll mostly fail while
succeeding every now and then.
Later on, you'll succeed most of the time
and fail rarely.
You'll still fail at times,
but your life would have changed a lot.
An inflexible woman would have become?
a very flexible person.
(Audience Laughter)
A stubborn man would have become a sweet
person. (Audience Laughter)
You would have become soft, and yet it
wouldn't mean you are weak.
Your mind would have been trained to be
soft and flexible.
The change will be good for yourself.
Others will also acknowledge the change.
'oh? are you about to die?'
(Audience Laughter)
'you have changed'
It's very difficult to change a person.
Old proverbs say that one only changes
once he/she is near death.
So when someone changes,
people say 'Is he/she near death or what?'
(Audience Laughter)
But through practice, we can change
without dying.
We become reborn.
This is why we receive a new dharma name.
We become reborn without changing our
bodies.
We basically change our fortunes through
our own will.
This is ultimately where our practice
should lead us.
You said you end up hating yourself.
Hating yourself is the same as hating
others.
You hate others when you can't control
them the way you want.
You hate yourself when you can't control
yourself the way you want.
It stems from the same psychology.
You get angry when you
can't have others follow your way.
You regret when you can't control your
own self.
And yet you can neither control others
nor yourself the way you want.
Accept whatever happens.
If you've made a mistake, don't think
much of it.
Acknowledge it as is and let it go.
Think of trying again.
Thinking you're a fool to have made a mistake
is negative thinking.
It makes you despair.
Your life darkens, you loose energy.
Think of starting a new instead.
Think, 'Ah, it didn't work this time.
Lets try again.'
Once you do, you find hope and energy.
Your face becomes brighter.
Though you may be failing,
your face lights up with hope.
that is all to it
Hence failure becomes the mother of
success.
Failure doesn't lead to defeat,
It leads to success.
When kids start riding bikes for the
first time,
do they not fall many times?
They do, don't they?
And yet they have fun trying and falling
all day.
They don't mind getting their
knees bruised.
Despite falling down, they get right back
on.
They are never pessimistic.
Failure becomes the mother of
their success.
Falling again and again and again
and again
ultimately results in riding.
Hence from a positive standpoint,
falling becomes a necessary
process to riding.
Kids try again and again and again after each fall,
they don't kick their bikes in defeat.
They don't say, 'I can't do this.'
They learn to ride by trying again and
and again after each fall.
But what happens when greed takes over?
You try a few times and throw a tantrum.